Hi, this is Matt Baker. Today, I'm going
to show you the family tree of Japanese
emperors. Unlike in other monarchies,
every single Japanese monarch has
belonged to just one male-line dynasty,
the Yamato dynasty, which goes back at
least 1,500 years, making it the
longest-reigning dynasty of all time.
Japan is also unique in that it's the
only surviving monarchy whose monarch
still holds the title of emperor. Now,
throughout Japan's long history, there
were actually several periods in which
the country also had a shogun, a shogun
being a type of hereditary dictator. So,
take note that I'll be showing the
family tree of them as well. For most of
the video, I'll be using this brand new
chart titled East Asian Royal Family
Trees, which is the first of at least
two charts that will replace our old
Asian Royal Family Trees poster. This
new one focuses mainly on China, Korea,
and Japan, as well as the Mongol Empire
and Tibet. Later this year, I hope to
release a separate chart focusing on the
Islamic dynasties of West Asia. If you
want to get a copy of the new chart,
just head over to usefulcharts.com
using the link in the description or
pinned comment. There, you'll find all
of the charts that we sell, as well as
some free stuff, too. So, definitely go
check it out. Again, that's
usefulcharts.com.
Okay, we're going to start not with an
emperor, but rather a prince named
Shotoku. He lived during the Asuka
period, which is when Japan went from
having several kingdoms to having just
one, the one ruled by the Yamato
dynasty. Shotoku was the grandson of
Kinmei, who is generally seen as being
the earliest member of the dynasty to be
indisputably historical, rather than
legendary. Now, the reason why I'm
starting with Shotoku is because of a
diplomatic letter he wrote in the year
607 on behalf of his aunt Suiko to the
emperor of China, which famously started
with from the sovereign of the land of
the rising sun to the sovereign of the
land of the setting sun. These words are
important for two reasons. First, it's
where the name Japan comes from, which
is actually just a foreign pronunciation
of Nippon or Nihon, which means land of
the rising sun. Second, this letter
marks an important turning point in East
Asian history because for the first time
ever, the Japanese monarch is basically
saying to the Chinese monarch, "I'm your
equal." Now, Shotoku is also important
because he lived during the time when
Buddhism was being introduced to Japan,
and when it was not yet certain whether
or not Buddhism would gain a foothold.
You see, during the early Asuka period,
there were two rival clans who were both
trying to influence the direction of the
country. The Soga clan wanted to promote
Buddhism, whereas the Mononobe clan
wanted to stick with traditional
Shintoism. Shotoku was a Soga on his
mother's side, and therefore when the
Soga ended up winning the conflict, he
helped integrate Buddhist ideas into the
structure of the government. Now,
although all of these monarchs during
the Asuka period are now considered to
have been emperors, during their
lifetimes they were actually not. During
their reigns, the title they used was
actually great king of Yamato. It wasn't
until the reign of Tenmu that they
switched to calling themselves emperors,
the Japanese word being tenno. You see,
slowly Japan was modeling itself on Tang
China, which basically meant greater
centralization of power with the
Imperial Court being the one holding all
of that centralized power. The last step
of the process was moving to a new
capital city, which occurred during the
reign of Empress Genmei. This also
marked the beginning of a new period
known as the Nara period. From here
onwards on this chart, all of the
Japanese emperors will be shown in
yellow boxes, sometimes with a picture
as well. During the reigns of Genmei and
her daughter Gensho, Japan's two oldest
surviving texts were published, the
Kojiki and the Nihon Shoki. Like the
Hebrew Bible, these two books mix
mythology and legend with a bit of real
history with the goal being to show that
the Yamato dynasty had a divine right to
rule. According to the Kojiki and Nihon
Shoki, the very first emperor of Japan
was a man named Jimmu, who lived during
the 600s BCE, and who was a direct
descendant of Amaterasu, the Japanese
goddess of the sun. He's then followed
by a long list of additional
mythological and legendary rulers, but
by the time we get to Yuryaku around the
400s CE, we start to approach real
history. And by the time we get to
Kinmei, well, like I said earlier, by
this point we are definitely dealing
with real history, which is why he's
shown at the top of our chart. Now, one
important thing to note about Japanese
empresses is that they never actually
break the male line succession. While
they do reign in their own right, the
line always eventually moves back to a
male line member of the Yamato dynasty.
So, after Empress Gensho, the throne
went to her nephew Shomu. And then,
after his daughter, who reigned twice,
it moved all the way over here and on to
Kanmu. During the reign of Kanmu, the
capital of Japan was once again moved,
this time to the city now known as
Kyoto, where it would remain for the
next 1,074 years. We thus enter a new
period in Japanese history known as the
Heian period, Heian meaning peace. One
of the defining features of the Heian
period, besides the fact that it was
mostly peaceful, was the dominance of
the Fujiwara clan who had earlier helped
to get rid of the Soga clan. One of the
things that the Fujiwara's did was stop
the practice of having empresses reign
in situations where a male line member
of the dynasty was not yet ready.
Instead, in these situations, they took
on the role of regent. They also
consistently married their daughters to
emperors, and thus eventually the role
of the emperor was reduced to that of a
figurehead with the Fujiwara's holding
all of the real power. One example of
them using their power occurred during
the reign of Emperor Seiwa's son, Yozei,
who started at just 9 years old. He
supposedly showed signs of mental
instability, and therefore his Fujiwara
regent had him deposed, moving the
succession to a different branch of the
Yamato tree. However, the Seiwa line
continued through his son, Sadazumi,
eventually becoming the main part of the
Minamoto clan. You see, as the Imperial
family grew, some parts of the tree
ended up being spun off to form certain
high-ranking aristocratic clans. Another
example of this can be seen up here,
where the descendants of one of Kanmu's
younger sons, Kuzuhara, ended up part of
the Taira clan. Now, we'll be coming
back to the Minamoto and Taira in a bit,
but for now, I want to point out Daigo,
who was one of the few emperors during
this period who ruled on his own without
the Fujiwara's. I also want to mention
that it was during the Heian period that
a lot of the core aspects of Japanese
culture, as distinct from Chinese
culture, were formulated, such as the
Katakana and Hiragana scripts. If you're
interested in learning those, I suggest
you check out our Writing Systems of the
World poster, which I'll link to in the
description. It was in Hiragana,
originally considered as a script for
women only, that The Tale of Genji was
written, authored by Lady Murasaki, who
lived during the reign of Emperor
Ichijo. Her book is considered to be the
world's first-ever novel, as well as
Japan's greatest work of literature. An
early illustrated copy of the novel has
survived to this day and is a good
example of the Yamato-e art style, yet
another aspect of Japanese culture that
originated in the Heian period. Now,
when it comes to the dominance of the
Fujiwara clan, that started to decline
around the time of Emperor Shirakawa,
who was the first emperor to retire to a
monastery, but then act as the power
behind the throne for the rest of his
life, a practice called cloistered rule,
which was also used by Emperors Toba and
Go-Shirakawa.
Take note that the prefix Go, which
you'll see a lot of from here on out,
means later. So, in other words,
Go-Shirakawa basically means Shirakawa
the second. The other thing that led to
the decline of the Fujiwara was the
rising power of several new military
clans, which were made up of
professional warriors, the most elite of
which were known as samurais. The two
most important, which I've already
mentioned, were the Minamoto and the
Taira. Initially, it was the Taira who
wielded the most influence, with Taira
no Kiyomori becoming Japan's de facto
ruler in 1167, and his grandson Antoku
becoming emperor in 1180. But, the
Minamoto were not happy with this, and
thus a civil war ensued, known as the
Genpei War, which is described in the
epic The Tale of the Heike. The Minamoto
eventually won the war under the
leadership of Minamoto no Yoritomo. As
soon as retired emperor Go-Shirakawa
died, Yoritomo became Japan's new
military dictator, this time taking the
title of shogun, and this time passing
the role on hereditarily. Thus, began
the Kamakura shogunate, as well as the
Kamakura period, both named after the
city of Kamakura, which is where the
shogun had his headquarters. Take note
that this point on the chart also marks
the transition between classical Japan
and medieval, or feudal, Japan. Okay, so
the ironic thing about the Kamakura
shoguns is that, while they managed to
once again reduce the emperor to just a
figurehead, they themselves ended up
being reduced to just figureheads as
well, shortly after the death of
Yoritomo. You see, on their mother's
side, the next two shoguns were
descendants of the Hojo clan, and
because they were minors, it was their
maternal grandfather, Hojo Tokimasa, who
ended up becoming the real ruler,
passing on his power to his descendants.
As you can see here, after Sanetomo, the
title of shogun actually passed to some
minor relatives, and then to the
imperial family itself. So, you'll have
to end up with a situation in which one
brother was the emperor, and another
brother the shogun, with the real power
being held by the Hojos. The most
important Hojo ruler ended up being Hojo
Tokimune, who served during the time
when Prince Koreyasu was the shogun. You
see, during his tenure, the Mongols
attacked Japan twice. But, both times,
Hojo Tokimune managed to repel them.
Although, both times the seasonal
typhoon also played a role. The Hojos'
grip on power lasted until the reign of
Go-Daigo, who in 1331
attempted to overthrow the Hojos as well
as the Kamakura shogunate. At first, he
failed and was replaced by an emperor
from a different branch of the family.
But then, 2 years later, he was
successful thanks to the help of a
samurai named Ashikaga
This led to a 3-year period known as the
Kenmu Restoration, in which the emperor,
meaning Go-Daigo, was finally the actual
ruler of Japan. But then, his former
ally, Ashikaga Takauji, betrayed him,
seizing power for himself and founding a
new shogunate known as the Ashikaga
shogunate. Although, take note that the
associated period is called the
Muromachi period after the location of
their headquarters. Interestingly, the
Ashikaga shoguns were actually distant
relatives of the original Kamakura
shoguns because they were both
descendants of this Minamoto samurai
here. And of course, they were also
distant relatives of the current
emperors because remember, this branch
of the Minamoto clan were the
descendants of Emperor Seiwa. Okay,
going back to the Muromachi period,
you'll notice that it coincided with a
strange situation, in which there ended
up being two emperors at the same time,
both claiming to be the legitimate one.
The descendants of Kogon remained in
Kyoto, supported by the new shoguns.
Thus, they are known as the Northern
Court, in contrast to the descendants of
Go-Daigo, who are known as the Southern
Court, because they fled south and set
up a rival court in Yoshino. Now, even
though the Southern Court were the
fleeing rivals, they are today seen as
having been the legitimate emperors of
Japan, because they were the ones who
kept hold of the official Imperial
Regalia. After around 60 years of the
split, a peace treaty was negotiated by
the shogun Ashikaga Yoshimitsu, and the
two courts were unified with the
Northern Emperor Go-Komatsu being made
the sole emperor. However, his male line
died out after the reign of his son
Shoko. So, after Shoko, the throne
passed to this line instead, with the
next two emperors being Go-Hanazono and
Go-Tsuchimikado,
both of whom had very long reigns at
about 36 years each. Go-Tsuchimikado's
reign coincided with the tenure of
Ashikaga Yoshimasa as shogun. Yoshimasa
is an interesting figure, because on one
hand, he's seen as being the worst
shogun in all of Japanese history, his
mismanagement resulting in the 150-year
long Warring States period. But, on the
other hand, he helped lay the
foundations for many things that are
seen today as core aspects of Japanese
traditional culture, such as the chanoyu
tea ceremony, the wabi-sabi aesthetic,
Noh theater, and ikebana flower
arranging. The Warring States period
came to an end thanks to a series of
leaders known as Japan's Three Great
Unifiers: Oda Nobunaga, Toyotomi
Hideyoshi and Tokugawa Ieyasu, the last
of whom became the founder of Japan's
third and final shogunate, the Tokugawa
shogunate, which coincided with the Edo
period, once again named for the city
where the shogunate had its capital.
Take note that Edo was the original name
for Tokyo. The Edo period in Japan is
known for its strict policy of sakoku,
which literally means locked country.
You see, during the mid-1500s, the first
Europeans landed in Japan, including
several Catholic missionaries, mostly
Jesuits from Spain and Portugal. The new
shogun saw this as a threat to Japan's
political structures and culture. So,
they instigated a policy of
isolationism. Now, keep in mind that
Japan was not totally isolated during
this period. Trade was maintained with
China, Korea, and the Dutch Republic.
And through these connections, new
scientific knowledge from the outside
continued to make its way to Japan.
Unlike during the previous two
shogunates, the Tokugawa shogunate, or
Edo period, was mostly peaceful. And
during this time, Japan started to
transition from a mostly rural state
into a more urbanized state. During this
period, Japan also got its first
reigning empresses in over 850 years,
starting with Empress Meisho and then
later Empress Go-Sakuramachi,
who reigned until which time Go-Momozono
was ready to rule, and then later served
as mentor to Emperor Kokaku during the
early years of his reign, when there was
a major famine. Because of her
compassion, wisdom, and diplomacy
skills, she is remembered to this day as
Japan's national mother. Kokaku ended up
having a long reign, in fact, the
longest ever reign up to that point at
37 years. He was followed by his son
Ninko, and then grandson Komei. During
the reign of Komei, when Tokugawa Iesada
was shogun, a famous event known as the
Black Ship Incident occurred, when a US
Navy captain named Matthew Perry entered
Edo's harbor with two heavily armed
steamships pumping black smoke into the
air. He met with the shogun and
basically forced him to sign a treaty,
effectively ending Japan's policy of
isolationism.
About a decade later, Emperor Meiji came
to the throne, and it was Meiji who
would become the most important Japanese
emperor of all time. You see, he and his
leading officials initiated the Meiji
Restoration, putting an end to the
Tokugawa shogunate, and putting power
back into the hands of the Imperial
Court. He moved the court from Kyoto to
Edo, renaming the city as Tokyo, which
literally means Eastern Capital. From
there, Meiji managed to industrialize
and modernize Japan at an incredible
pace, taking it from a feudal state run
by samurai warriors to a more
western-like country with a strong
modern military. Unlike many other Asian
countries, instead of being colonized,
Japan under Meiji became a colonizer,
taking over the northern island of
Hokkaido, the kingdom of Ryukyu, which
included Okinawa, Taiwan, also known at
the time as Formosa, and then finally,
Korea. Meiji was followed by his son
Taisho, and then by Taisho's son Showa,
better known as Hirohito. You see,
whenever Japan gets a new emperor, a
proclamation is made announcing the name
of a new era. In the past, the name of
the emperor and the name of the era were
different. But ever since Meiji, Japan
now has a custom whereby emperors are
renamed after death so that their name
then matches their era name. So, for
example, during his lifetime, Meiji was
actually known as Mutsuhito. Likewise,
Taisho was known as Yoshihito and Showa
as Hirohito. During the early reign of
Hirohito, Japan continued to expand
taking over Manchuria in 1931 and much
of mainland China in 1937, which is when
the Nanjing Massacre occurred. Then,
during World War II, it took over most
of Southeast Asia as well as many
Pacific islands, even famously attacking
Pearl Harbor in December 1941. Of
course, we know what happened after
that. The US entered the war, eventually
dropping nuclear bombs on Hiroshima and
Nagasaki, forcing Japan to surrender. At
this point, Japan was reduced back to
its four main islands as well as some
other minor islands nearby. In 1947,
Japan also became a parliamentary
monarchy, meaning that the emperor was
once again reduced to being a figurehead
with an elected parliament now holding
the real power. Hirohito remained
emperor and reigned until his death in
1989, giving him a total reign of 62
years, which is the current record for a
Japanese emperor. He was followed by his
son, Akihito, who reigned until 2019, at
which time he became the first emperor
to resign in over 200 years. He is still
living, aged 92, but the current
reigning emperor is now his son,
Naruhito. Upon Akihito's death, he will
be remembered as Heisei, but it is
considered very inappropriate to refer
to him by that name now. Likewise,
Naruhito will eventually be known as
Reiwa, but at the moment, that is simply
just the era name, not his regnal name.
Now, as things stand, the future of the
Japanese monarchy is a bit uncertain,
mostly because Naruhito, who is 66, has
just one child, his 24-year-old
daughter, Aiko. And there are currently
only three males who are even eligible
to become emperor in the future. First
in the line of succession is Naruhito's
60-year-old brother, Fumihito. Second is
Fumihito's 19-year-old son, Hisahito.
And third is Naruhito's 90-year-old
childless uncle, Masahito. Masahito is
obviously unlikely to ever become
emperor, nor is Fumihito, considering
he's about the same age as Naruhito. And
therefore, the future of the Japanese
monarchy currently rests on just one
young boy, Hisahito. But then, on top of
this, there's the fact that around 75%
of Japanese citizens would like to see
Aiko become empress, and the rules
changed like they have in other
countries, so that succession can be
based on absolute primogeniture, instead
of male-only primogeniture. But what
would happen if that wasn't allowed, and
something happened to young Hisahito? Is
there any other option? Well,
surprisingly, we have to go back a long
way on the family tree before we can
find any minor branches that still have
male-line descendants. In fact, you have
to go all the way back to the brother of
Go Hanazono who lived over 500 years
ago. If we move over to this chart here,
you can see that Go Hanazono had a
brother named Sadatsune. Well, the
descendants of Sadatsune, shown in red,
became one of four branches of the
Imperial Family called Shinoke, which
used to be eligible for the throne. That
eligibility being taken away in 1947.
The other three Shinoke lines have all
since gone ex- tinct. But, the red line
still exists. The most senior person now
being Hiroaki, who was born a prince,
but then had his titles taken away in
1947.
Hiroaki is currently 94, and he had no
sons. So, the next most senior male-line
descendant would have to be found among
one of these gray lines, which used to
be known as Oke. Several of these
branches, such as this one, have
continued in the male line. So, it has
been suggested that a current member of
the Imperial Family could adopt someone
from one of these lines, so that the
future of the Yamato Dynasty could be
made more certain. Well, what do you
think? Should Princess Aiko be allowed
to become Empress? Or should Japan pin
all of its hopes on Prince Hisahito?
Should the distant members of the
Imperial Family be reinstated and/or
adopted, just in case? Or should Japan
get rid of its monarchy all together?
Let me know in the comments what your
opinion is. And don't forget, if you
want to get a copy of the new chart, be
sure to click the link in the
description, or just head over to
usefulcharts.com.
Take note that the poster is printed on
thick, high-quality paper at an
amazingly high resolution. So, not only
is the chart durable, it looks great,
too. Again, just click the link in the
description or pinned comment, or the
icon you'll see on screen right now.
Thanks for watching.